<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A companion for prayer, or, Directions for improvement in grace and practical Godliness in time of extraordinary danger by Richard Allein.</title>
            <author>R. A. (Richard Alleine), 1611-1681.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26705</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A985</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19955</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08038046</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08038046</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40750</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26705)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40750)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 679:32b or 1221:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A companion for prayer, or, Directions for improvement in grace and practical Godliness in time of extraordinary danger by Richard Allein.</title>
                  <author>R. A. (Richard Alleine), 1611-1681.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.R. for T.C.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of originals in the Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 679 is bound following: Instructions about heart-work / by ... Richard Allein ... London : Printed by J.R. for Thomas Cockeril ..., 1684.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional exercises.</term>
               <term>Spiritual life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40750:1"/>
            <p>A COMPANION FOR PRAYER OR, Directions for Improvement in Grace, and Practical God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs in time of Extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Danger.</p>
            <p>By <hi>RICHARD ALLEIN,</hi> Author of <hi>Vinditiae Pietatis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. R.</hi> for <hi>T. G.</hi> MDCLXXXIV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40750:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40750:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reverend Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE motion made in yours concerning Prayer, hath much affected me, and hath occaſioned some workings of my thoughts, which though (in a conſcience of mine own weakneſs I more than once laid aſide, yet they still return'd upon me; and I do now here offer the reſult of them to your Conſideration.</p>
            <p>We all know and teach, that they are only returning and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Prayers that will prevail with God; and 'tis to be doubted, that in this dead and decayed age there are too many profeſſors who will joyn in the deſign of Prayer, whom this must ſerve inſtead of
<pb facs="tcp:40750:3"/>Reformation, 'tis to ſuch eſpecially that the Directions in the incloſed Papers are intended. I ſend them to you, deſiring you to read them, and then to do what you pleaſe with them; beſeeching you, and truſting upon your friendly faithfulneſs here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, thar you will take your full free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, either to keep them in ſilence to your ſelf, or elſe to communicate and make them publick. I ſhould thankfully accent of any expung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, alterations or additions that you ſhall think needful. The Lord pardon the failings, and accent the ſincere aims of my ſoul herein. To his Grace I commend you, and in him I reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Dear Sir,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi> Your unworthy Friend and Servant,</hi> RICHARD ALLEIN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40750:3"/>
            <head>A COMPANION FOR PRAYER OR, Directions for Improvement in Grace and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Godlineſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>TO make way for, and to preſs to the diligent obſerving the following Directions, let theſe things be premiſed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the Power of Religion is much fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, at leaſt is at a ſtand, amongſt multitudes of Profeſſors in <hi>England.</hi> Sure this needs no proof, when we have ſo many ſad ocular Demonſtrations hereof before us.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That for this, the Lord hath a controverſie with us at this day, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.4. Whatever controverſie the Lord hath with the <hi>Belials</hi> amongſt us, whoſe horrible wickedneſs hath even repined them for vengeance, his ſpecial quarrel ſeems to be with his own people. We may gueſs againſt whom the ſpecial anger is, by obſerving at whoſe faces chiefly his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows are levelled. Againſt whom do our enemies (the rod of his anger) make a wide mouth, and draw forth the tongue, and lift up their fierceſt hands?</p>
            <p n="3">3. No Prayers will avail, nor have the leaſt help in them, but the Prayers of ſuch, with whom the Lords controverſie is taken up and compoſed; thoſe with whom he hath a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular quarrel, are like to be unhappy Mediators for others. We chuſe the ſavourites of Princes to be our Interceſſors with them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. There can he no taking up Gods controverſie, unleſs the matter of it be removed by repentance and reformation,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40750:4"/>
               <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.15, 16, 18. <hi>When ye make many prayers, I will not hear, your hands are full of blood; waſh ye, make you clean,</hi> &amp;c <hi>Come now, and let us reaſon together.</hi> Joſh. 7.10. <hi>Get thee up; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore lieſt thou thus upon thy face? Iſrael hath ſinned</hi>— they have taken the accurſed thing; and <hi>v.</hi> 12. <hi>I will not be with you any more, except the accurſed thing be deſtroyed from amongſt you.</hi> Is there no accurſed thing amongſt, even the Profeſſors of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion! Behold! the wedg of Gold, and the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, their pride and their covetouſneſs, hid in their hearts for a tent. Go ſearch out theſe, and every other accurſed thing within you, let them be deſtroyed if ye would have the Lord to be at peace.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If there may be ſuch a ſpirit of Prayer ſtir'd up amongſt us, as may have his fruit unto Holineſs, and real reformation of the evils of our ways; this would comfort us, and give us great hopes in the hardeſt caſes.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Therefore in all our crying to God for his help, in caſe of publick fears, dangers or diſtreſſes, our eye ſhould be firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon, and we ſhould wreſtle with the Lord for the pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, purging, and ſanctification of our own hearts and lives; wherein if we prevail not, we ſhall be as a rotten tooth, or a bone out of joynt, for any help there is in us, or in any thing we do; unleſs we can pray up a ſpirit of Holineſs in our ſelves, a ſpirit of Love, and of Power, and of a ſound mind, we are not like to do any thing to purpoſe, in praying down Mercy for the people; the Devil will give us leave to vifit the Throne of Grace, ſo we will but carry our hard and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed hearts with us; if we cannot get to be of the Lords holy Ones, though we make many Prayers, he will not hear, here the intereſt and the hopes of the people of God lye, in the ſhedding abroad of the ſanctifying and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſpirit upon them; for this therefore ſhould we firſtly pray.</p>
            <p n="7">7. 'Tis not praying alone that will do: to the bringing on our Reformation, there muſt be alſo a conſtant and ſedulous uſe of all Gods other means, in our whole courſe of Life.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Some of theſe means are preſented in the following Directions.</p>
            <div type="directions">
               <head>
                  <hi>1.</hi> General Directions.</head>
               <p>Direct. 1. <hi>Take up a deep and ſerious deſign of making an advance in ſerious Religion.</hi> Sit not down by, take not up with what you have already attained, but reſolve for reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forward, and following after towards that which you have not attained; content not your ſelves to drive gently
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40750:4"/>on, as your fleſh will bear, but ſtir up your ſelves to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low hard after the Lord; and let this be the deliberate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree and intent of your hearts. Say to thine heart, How is it with me? Doth my Soul proſper? Are my ways ſuch as pleaſe the Lord? What is mine expectation and mine hope? What is the aim and buſineſs of my life? Is it that Chriſt may be magnified by me, and that I may be made partaker of his Holineſs, and ſhew forth his Vertues in my generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Can I ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>To me to live is Chriſt?</hi> Ah wretch that I am! how deeply hath this ſelf, and this world gone ſhares with my Lord! O! how little of my time, my parts, my ſtrength, yea, and of my very heart alſo have been incloſed and conſecrated as Holineſs to the Lord! how much of me hath been left out in common for the world? Well, but what meaneſt thou for the future? Wilt thou hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth change the purpoſe and intent of thine heart? Come man, wilt take up a deſign for, and henceforth determine and ſet thine heart upon a more watchful, fruitful, and heavenly life? If thou wilt not be brought to decree, and reſolve upon a better life, much leſs wilt thou be perſwaded actually to it. What's begun well, is half done; and an holy deſign deeply laid, is a good beginning.</p>
               <p>Direct. 2. <hi>Let Gods Calls to extraordinary prayer, and a ſenſe of the neceſſity of your recovery and reformation, to your prevailing in prayer, quicken you on in the vigorous purſuance of your holy deſign.</hi> Now is a time wherein you have your hearts at the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, having ſuch weighty arguments before you, and the opportunity of doing two ſuch great things more, as the ſaving of your ſelves, and alſo of the people, both from ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and calamity.</p>
               <p>Direct 2. <hi>Do all you do, in purſuance hereof, in the name of the Lord Jeſus.</hi> He not diſcouraged at any proſpect: of difficulty, truſt in him for his help. Encourage your hearts with the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.13. <hi>I ſhall be able to do all things through Chriſt that ſtrengthens me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Direct. 4. <hi>Keep your e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e and your heart much upon God and the other world;</hi> Be able to ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.20. <hi>Our Converſation is in Heaven;</hi> that is, there the buſineſs of our life lies; and that not only above ſpiritual and heavenly things, but with God himſelf. Live at the fountain and ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40750:5"/>thence all your light, and life, and holineſs, and ſtrength muſt flow down. Be much in looking upwards; and beholding in a glaſs the glory of the Lord, you will be chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged from Glory to glory, into the ſame Image, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. Look much and often upon the things that are not ſeen, if ye would be delivered from the power and malign influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the things that are ſeen; let your eye be upon the Sun, and you will ſee a dimneſs and darkneſs upon the Earth; get you cloathed with the Sun, and you will get the Moon under your feet.</p>
               <p>Direct. 5. <hi>See that there be no allowed ſin in your hearts or practice,</hi> Pſal. 66.18. <hi>If I regard Iniquity in mine heart, God will not hear my prayer,</hi> nor help me. An allowed ſin is as the dead fleſh in the wound; whatever methods or medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines be taken, there will be no healing till the dead fleſh be eaten off; you may profeſs, and pray, and hear all your life long, and yet will never proſper whileſt you are privy to any one indulged ſin.</p>
               <p>Direct. 6. <hi>Be conſtant and inſtant in dayly, ſecret, and family prayer.</hi> Let not extraordinary Prayer excuſe your ordinary; and let not your neglect of ordinary Prayer unfit you for extraordinary; Let not your way to your Cloſet be untrod. He that holds his acquaintance in Heaven by being often with God, will be the moſt like to prevail with God in the moſt preſſing and difficult caſes; thoſe that are much in Prayer, thoſe are the men that uſe to be mighty in Prayer.</p>
               <p>Direct. 7. <hi>In all your praying, both ordinary and extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, let your eye be,</hi> (I ſay not chiefly, but) <hi>firſtly upon the caſe of your own Souls:</hi> What improvement you obtain here will be of this double advantage; 1. There will be the more hope of your being heard for the publick. 2. If the Lord be not prevailed with for publick mercies and deliverances, yet you will be the better prepared for ſufferings. If God ſhould ſhew mercy as to the publick, ſhould ſcatter our clouds, and blow over our ſtorms, ſhould cauſe our light to break forth as the morning, and our righteouſneſs alſo as the noon-day; yet what would all this be to thee, who art unrighteous? What would it be to thee, if in all the Land of <hi>Goſhen</hi> there ſhould be light, and thou in the midſt thereof ſhouldeſt be cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red over with the darkneſs of <hi>Egypt;</hi> if there ſhould be dew on all the graſs of the field, and thy fleece only ſhould be dry?
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40750:5"/>if thou ſhouldeſt live to ſee thy people a ſaved people, and an holy and fruitful Nation, and thou ſhould'ſt ſtand as a withered and dry Tree amongſt all the flouriſhing Cedars? Get up thine own heart into good proof; or whatever ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual plenty thou maiſt ſee in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> yet thou wilt not eat thereof. Talk no more of thine hopes of ſeeing good days, how little would that be to thee, unleſs thou get thee a better heart?</p>
               <p>Direct. 8. <hi>Let you prayers be followed with a conſtant care of your ways.</hi> Let not your praying ſerve you inſtead of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and reforming, but let it quicken you to your whole duty; let your entring into your Cloſet be your aſcending heavenwards; and let not your returns thence be the falling down of your Souls from Heaven to Earth. Let your duties and ways he all of a piece; live like praying Chriſtians. Let not the ſpirituality of your mornings and evenings, counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance or encourage you in your all-day carnality. <hi>Be in the fear of the Lord all the day long,</hi> Prov. 23.17.</p>
               <p>Direct. 9. <hi>Whatever incomes you receive from God into your own Souls, be free in diſperſing to others:</hi> I mean in away of holy diſcourſe and conference. Diſperſing and communicating is the beſt way to thriving, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.24. <hi>There is that ſcatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and yet increaſeth; there is that withholdeth, and it tendeth to poverty.</hi> 'Tis true with reſpect to ſpirituals as well as to tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals. There are none that grow more rich towards God, than thoſe, who by bringing forth what they have received, labour to make others rich alſo. Give the holy fire within you a vent, and it will burn the clearer. Keep not your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to your ſelves; let your full cup run over, let your lips drop as the honey-comb, let your mouth be a well of life, and your lips feed many, <hi>Prov.</hi> 10.11. Build up one another in the moſt Holy Faith; provoke one another to love and to good works; let your Families, your Wives and Children, your Neighbours and Acquaintance, have light from your Candle, and be warmed by your Fire. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs its one ſpecial part of Gods quarrel with Chriſtians, That they are ſo very many of them, of ſuch carnal and unſavoury converſes. Is it <hi>[thy]</hi> caſe? haſt thou this to charge upon thy ſelf? O! amend, amend, and ſee that thou continue not ſuch a barren Soul; as low as 'tis with thee in grace, think not to riſe high, unleſs thou wilt make better uſe of what thou haſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="directions">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:40750:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Particular Directions.</head>
               <p>Direct. 1. <hi>Conſider what it is whereto you have already attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and be thankful; and thence be encouraged to preſs on, and hope for more.</hi> Haſt thou obtained Grace from the Lord? and hath he cauſed his Grace to abound towards thee, and in thee? and haſt thou a witneſs within thee that thou haſt not received the Grace of God in vain? But doſt thou ſtudy to walk worthy of that Grace wherein thou ſtandeſt? O re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in the Lord, and let all within thee bleſs his Holy Name; and take what thou haſt thus received as an earneſt of more. Set thy foot upon the neck of every mortified luſt, take the more heart to thee to go on in the fight, and rejoyce in hope of a total and final victory, The Soldier, when one Wing of his Enemies Army is routed, or they do but give ground, and begin to fall, this raiſes his cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and he falls more ſmartly on. Go thou and do like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; and let thy beginning, much more thy growth in Grace, and thy experiences hereof, be the oiling of thy wheels, for thy more vigorous following on after, yet a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter increaſe.</p>
               <p>Direct. 2. <hi>Conſider what your ſpecial corruptions, infirmities, wants, neglects, temptations, or your moſt ordinary falls are.</hi> 1. What your ſpecial corruptions are, how far forth you have conquered them, and where you ſtick. In ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, Pride; in others Covetouſneſs; in others, Senſuality; in others, Sloathfulneſs; in others, Peeviſhneſs, or Froward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or the like; may have gotten ſuch head in them, that theſe weeds overtop, and even choak up all their flowers. 2. What your ſpecial wants or weakneſſes are in point of Grace; what Graces they are, whether Faith, or Love, or Peacefulneſs, or Meekneſs, or Humility, or Patience, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> wherein you are moſt deficient or weak. 3. What Duties they are, as either Prayer, Meditation, Communing with your own hearts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which you are moſt apt to neglect, or find moſt difficult to go comfortably through. 4. What Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they are, by which you are moſt commonly aſſaulted or foiled. 5. What your moſt ordinary Falls are in point of practice. And here let Profeſſors of Religion be warned to confider, if they be not overtaken (beſides many others) by ſome of theſe fout evils. 1. An over-eager and gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy following after the World: The zeal of ſome mens ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40750:6"/>after riches, hath eaten up all their zeal of God. O! into what poverty hath thy Soul fallen, whilſt thou haſt been ſo buſie in the world, and haſt felt the proſperities thereof come crouding in upon thee! Some rich Profeſſors may remember the days of old, and be troubled. This thought, When I was but a little one in this world, then was it better with me than now; this thought may be an Arrow in their hearts, and kill the joy, and let out the juyce and ſweetneſs of their greateſt abundance. I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the kindneſs of my youth, and the love of mine eſpou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals; but O where am I now! my very riſing hath given me the fall. 2. A liberty for carnal jollity, a jovial and vainly mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry life, ſuch there are, who have leſt off to walk mournfully before the Lord of Hoſts, and have given themſelves to live merrily with the World ; who have given over to weep with them that weep, and are fallen in to laugh with them that laugh; to jeſt and ſport, and be vain with the vain ones, yea and it may be to drink and to ſit by it with thoſe that drink. It's now grown too creditable to frequent drinking Houſes: Tradeſmen that are Profeſſors, eſpecially in Cities or great Towns, how ordinarily do they, upon pretence of diſpatch of buſineſs, ſit many hours over a diſh of Coffee, or a Cup of Ale, or a glaſs of Sack; and carry it ſo, that they can hardly be diſtinguiſhed from the good Fellows of the world, but perhaps by this only, That they are not down-right drunken into Beaſts. If there be a liberty of ſuch Houſes, and meetings in them ſometimes neceſſary (as perhaps it may) yer let not this liberty be uſed as an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to the fleſh. 3. Gaudineſs or over-coſtlineſs in Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, wherein ſome of them glitter and ſhine amongſt the greateſt Gallants of the Earth. Some amongſt profeſſors do not only ſhun, but diſdain and deſpiſe the old ſelf-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al that was wont to be among Chriſtians in theſe and the like particulars, as if they were ſet at liberty by the Goſpel from the Laws of Chriſt, as well as from the Law of <hi>Moſes.</hi> To theſe three let me add one evil more: 4 . A neglect of your Families; of the Inſtructing, Catechiſing, and due diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them; the conſequents of which neglect are very ſadly to be ſeen in the ignorance, errors, rudeneſs and diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs abounding amongſt many of them: there are not a few who take ſome care of themſelves, but leave the bridle on the necks of theirs, and reap many heart-breaking crops in them, as the fruits of their own negligence. O let holy <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s reſolution be yours: <hi>As for me and mine houſe, we will ſerve the Lord.</hi> Joſh. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.15.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:40750:7"/>
Now diligently ſearch and conſider thy ſelf in all theſe things; and when thou haſt faithfully ſtudied thy ſelf and thy ways, and haſt found what it is that thou art moſt pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant or wanting in, and moſt prejudiced and hindred by; then conclude, <hi>here my great difficulty lyes,</hi> and therefore here my great work lies, if ever I would proſper, to get this or that corruption to be mortified, this or that grace ſtrengthened, ſuch and ſuch temptations to be ſhunned or provided againſt, and ſuch and ſuch faults to be amended, now I have found what hinders me; and that which doth hinder, will hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, till it be taken out of the way.</p>
               <p>Direct. 3. <hi>Bend the main force of all your Religion upon thoſe very points wherein yon are moſt failing or faulty.</hi> The Devil will allow us to be buſie in other matters of Religion, ſo he can but keep us off from thoſe things where our great ſtreſſes lies: And the deceitful heart will take up with that which is moſt eaſie and pleaſant, that thereby it may the better ſhift it ſelf of that which is more hard, and would go to the quick with it. We never purge or bleed to purpoſe, till we hit upon the right humour, and ſtrike the right vein.</p>
               <p>This is to act rationally, and in judgment; to bend our great ſtrength there, where our great difficulty or weakneſs bes. When you have by ſearching found out what you moſtly ſtick at: let it be your firſt grand errand in every Prayer, whether ordinary or extraordinary, to beg ſpecial help in this particular caſe: your weakneſs in any particular grace or duty, the power of any particular luſt, corruption, or temptation, your moſt ordinary and common falls in point of converſation; let theſe have a ſpecial place in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry prayer you make: And alſo let them be moſt needfully watched and laboured againſt in your lives. Turn in the ſtrength of Prayer, and watchfulneſs upon the ſtrength of Sin; let your main batteries be againſt the ſtrong holds; and where your walls are weakned, there ſet the ſtrongeſt guard and watch.</p>
               <p>Direct. 4. <hi>Meaſure your proficiency in Religion, by the power you get in thoſe particulars, wherein you have been moſt deficient or faulty,</hi> Judge not your ſelves by thoſe things which are moſt eaſie in Religion, but by your coming off in your moſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult caſe.</p>
               <p>Some profeſſors may at times ſeem to be full of good affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, ſtrangely elevated and enlarged in their prayers,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40750:7"/>yea, and to live in ſo great peace, as to take themſelves to have attained to the riches of full aſſurance, and yet for all this may be but very poor Chriſtians all the while. Let them be asked, How is it with your Soul? O! I bleſs the Lord, I find it very comfortable: I have ſweet communion with God in Prayer, and I live in the ſweet and refreſhing light of his countenance; he waſheth my ſteps with Butter, and his Sun ſhineth upon my paths; I thank the Lord I go comfortably on. But ſtay man, How is it with thine old corruptions? Thou wer't once intolerably proud, or fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, or earthly, or a jolly and vainly merry ſoul; what ground haſt thou gotten of thoſe very corruptions under which thou moſt groanedſt? How is it with thee with reſpect to temptation? Doſt thou fear and fly from temptation, and do what thou canſt to keep thy ſelf out of harms way? and when thou falleſt into temptation, when thou art actually tempted to Pride or Covetouſneſs, when thou art provoked to paſſion or impatience, how goes it with thee then? how ſtandeſt thou in the day of temptation? How is it with thee in regard of thy wonted evils in thy converſation? Haſt thou ſounded a retreat from thy eager chaſe after the great things of the world? Thou haſt been a zealot for encreaſing thine earthly Subſtance, art thou now become more mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate: Thou wert once a ſloathful, lazy foul in the matters of God, art thou now more diligent and induſtrious? art thou fervent in ſpirit, ſerving the Lord? Thou once livedſt a jolly, frothy and merry life, doſt thou now carry it with more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſs? Haſt thou left thy lying and deceitful dealing? Thou haſt been a ſelf-ſeeker, and a fleſh-pleaſer, but canſt ſay, through the Grace of God, I have now betaken my ſelf to a ſelf-denying-life; and doeſt thou deny thy ſelf in thoſe very things wherein thou wert uſed moſt to ſeek thy ſelf? Put thy ſelf upon a cloſe and ſevere trial here; and know that if the ſtrong hold be not battered and broken, if thine old luſts do ſtill hold their power in thee, if the old ſore be ſtill iſſuing out, the old ſtream be ſtill running its courſe; if thou canſt not ſay, I have kept me from <hi>[mine]</hi> iniquity, or at leaſt am ſighting more reſolvedly againſt it; if thou ſtill ſtickeſt where thou wert wont to ſtick (whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fluſh thou ſeemeſt to have of good affections, (whatſoever confidence thou haſt, of thy good condition) 'tis a ſure ſign it is not ſo well with thee. Look to what degree of ſucceſs thou haſt attained in thoſe things wherein thy great difficulty lay; to ſuch a degree of ſoul-proſperity thou haſt attained, and no more.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:40750:8"/>
Direct. 5. <hi>Meaſure your hopes of the Anſwer of your Prayers for the publick, by your experience of their ſpeeding in your own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular caſes.</hi> If thy ſin can ſtand before all thy prayers, thy Enemies, fears, and dangers are not like to fall ever the ſooner for ſuch praying; what God may do upon the prayers of others, thou knoweſt not; but nothing is like to go the better for thee. If thou haſt run with the foot men (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thee) and theſe have been too hard for thee, how wilt thou contend with them that ride upon horſes? If thou canſt not ſtop the muddy ſtreams of thine own ciſtern, how wilt thou ſtand before the ſwelling of <hi>Jordan?</hi> If thy prayers prevail ſo little to the ſetting thine own heart, or thine own houſe in order, how canſt think they will do any thing againſt the hoſts of the uncircumciſed; <hi>God heareth not ſinners;</hi> not only ſuch ſinners as are in a ſtate of ſin, and totally aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the life of God, but even ſuch alſo, who though for the main, they have been once waſhed in the blood of Chriſt, are again fallen into, and wallowing in the mud and mire of anyone allowed ſin; they are all like to be but mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable comforters in the day of diſtreſs. Remember that Scripture mentioned before, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 66.18. <hi>If I regard iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in my heart, God will not hear my prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But on the other ſide, if thou doſt obtain, if thou doſt prevail in thine own perſonal caſe, this hath good hope in it. 'Tis an argument that thy Prayers are accepted with God; and if the Lord accept thee when thou prayeſt for thy ſelf, or for thine houſe, thence the greater hope will ſpring that he will accept thee when thou prayeſt for his own houſe and people. And if he doth accept thee for them, he will ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deliver them out of their diſtreſs, and thou ſhalt have the honour to be one of thoſe for whoſe ſake deliverance comes; or if he ſhould not grant thy requeſt as to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, yet he will not fail to give thee thine own ſoul for a prey, though he do not give thee the lives of them that ſail with thee in the Ship.</p>
               <p>And now you ſee the beſt way that is open to you, to help at a pinch, to ſave the poor diſtreſſed Churches of God in this time of their need, ſuch praying as may have its fruit unto holineſs in your ſelves; by this you may do much to promote the holineſs and happineſs of the people; if any thing, this will do it.</p>
               <p>Wherefore gird up your loyns, and ſet in good earneſt upon this ſeaſonable and mighty duty. Go into your cloſets, liſt up your hearts, draw forth your ſouls; pour out your
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40750:8"/>tears, weep in your prayer, weep over your own and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſins and fears, and bow your ſelves with your might before the Lord; this once try what you can do, try the ſtrength of Prayer. Pray all to rights within you, and at home, and then ſeek and cry, and wreſtle, and truſt, and wait for the Salvation of God to be revealed in due time upon his people.</p>
               <p>Let us at length hear the concluſion of the whole matter, what ſhall be the fruit of all this: What will you now do? If I ſhould only ask, Who among you will join in, and pray, pray for the peace of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Church of the liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God? every one would readily anſwer, I will be for one, I for another, God forbid I ſhould hold my peace, I will pray for the peace of <hi>Jeruſalem, Let them proſper that love thee: Peace be within thy walls, and proſperity within thy Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces. For my Brethren and companions ſake I will pray, Peace be within thee, becauſe of the Houſe of the Lord our God, I will ſeek thy good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it be asked further, and who will pray for the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Babylon?</hi> O, every one of us that have an heart for the peace of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> Down with it, down with it even to the Ground. Remember, O Lord, the Children of <hi>Edom,</hi> in the day of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> who ſaid, Raze it, raze it even to the very ſoundation. O Daughter of <hi>Babylon</hi> that art to be deſtroyed, happy let him be that rewardeth thee as thou haſt ſerved us.</p>
               <p>But would you that your Prayers ſhould be heard? Then ariſe out of your places, and fall every man upon a perſonal Reformation. Down with your ſin, and out with the world; lift up Chriſt in your own hearts, if you would have Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt fall in the Earth; let Chriſt have a name within you above every name, and let every one that nameth the name of Chriſt depart from iniquity, from his own iniquity; ſeek not for Corn, and for wine, or for freedom to ſit down eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man under his own Vine, and under his own fig-tree, where none ſhall make them afraid; but ſeek the Lord, that the Lord God may dwell among you, may delight in you and be exalted by you, that you may indeed become the people of his Holineſs, and the people of his Prayer; ſeek to be made partakers of his holineſs, and follow after holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſo follow after that ye may obtain. Let there be ſuch a heart in you, and ſuch an holy deſign heartily taken up, and zealouſly purſued by you, and the Lord will certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accept you, and anſwer your prayers, and your prophane
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:40750:9"/>enemies will then learn to take heed how they again mock or boaſt themſelves againſt the Prayers of the Saints. It was reported of a great Church-man, that when ſeveral Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters were turn'd out of their places for non-conformity, he ſaid in diſdain, <hi>Wee'l turn them out, and let them ſee if they can pray them in again.</hi> Once lift up [holy] hands to the Lord, and God will give ſuch Anſwer, that they will take heed of boaſting again againſt Prayer. And if yet they ſhould take unto them the hardineſs, to ſay where is your God? Doubt not but in a little time you ſhall have this ſong put into your mouths, <hi>Lo this is our God, we have waited for him, and he will ſave us; this is the Lord, we have waited for him, we will be glad and rejoyce in his ſalvation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But if it muſt ſuffice you to pray, and you will ſtill go on to traverſe your old ways, ſuffering your ſins and the world to hold the head of you, let not ſuch men think they ſhall receive any thing of the Lord.</p>
               <p>Wherefore once again be exhorted to come to a point in this matter, and determine what ye will do; If ye will not heartily come in, in this neceſſary deſign of advancing in holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, you may even ſtand aſide, and ſit out from that of Prayer, for any good we can expect from you: But if you are reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved on the former, and that with all imaginable ſeriouſneſs, you will the more proſper in the latter; let both go together in one, and thenceforth look for good ſpeed in either.</p>
               <p>Well, ſhall this Decree immediately go forth? Say the word once, but let it be with an unalterable reſolution; at leaſt, be adviſed to this (which I pray forget not) from the day of your next ſolemn appearing before God in this duty of Prayer for the publick, let your Decree be dated; and if need be, let the very day be written down, and ſo go, and let it be heedfully proſecuted; and upon each re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn of this ſolemn ſervice, let it be actually and expreſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed. <hi>O Lord God of</hi> Abraham, Iſaac, <hi>and</hi> Iſrael, <hi>keep this for ever in the imagination of the thoughts of the heart of thy people and prepare their heart unto thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:40750:9"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
